{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Linear_Algebra — Slot 5 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Linear_Algebra — Slot 5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>If a square matrix \\(A\\) satisfies \\(A^TA=I\\), then the matrix \\(A\\) is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Idempotent</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Symmetric</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Orthogonal</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Hermitian</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Orthogonal</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49916/isro2008-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>If the two matrices \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;0 &amp;x \\\\ 0 &amp; x&amp; 1\\\\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; x \\end{bmatrix} \\text{and }\\begin{bmatrix} x &amp;1 &amp;0 \\\\ x &amp; 0&amp; 1\\\\ 0 &amp; x &amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) have the same determinant, then the value of  \\(x \\) is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\sqrt2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\pm \\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\pm \\frac{1}{\\sqrt2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/47590/isro2008-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>If M is a square matrix with a zero determinant, which of the following assertion (s) is (are) correct?<br>\nS1: Each row of M can be represented as a linear combination of the other rows<br>\nS2: Each column of M can be represented as a linear combination of the other columns<br>\nS3: M X=0 has a nontrivial solution<br>\nS4: M has an inverse<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>S3 and S2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>S1 and S4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>S1 and S3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>S1, S2 and S3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>S1, S2 and S3</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3319/gate2008-it-29\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>How many of the following matrices have an eigenvalue 1? <br>  \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0\\\\ 0&amp;0 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp; 1\\\\ 0&amp;0 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; -1\\\\ 1&amp;1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) and \\( \\begin{bmatrix} -1 &amp;0 \\\\ 1&amp;-1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>one</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>two</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>three</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>four</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>one</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/426/gate2008-28#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The following system of equations       <br>                                                                                      \\(x_{1}+x_{2}+2x_{3}=1 \\) <br> \\( x_{1}+2x_{2}+3x_{3}=2 \\) <br> \\(x_{1}+4x_{2}+\\alpha x_{3}=4\\)<br>\nhas a unique solution. The only possible value(s) for \\(\\alpha\\)  is/are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>either 0 or 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>one of 0, 1 or -1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>any real number other than 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>any real number other than 5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/401/gate2008-3#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Eigen vectors of \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;&amp; \\cos \\theta \\\\ \\cos \\theta &amp;&amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) are <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; 1 \\\\ 0 &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; n \\\\ 0 &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; na^{n-1} \\\\ 0 &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; na^{n-1} \\\\ -n &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; na^{n-1} \\\\ -n &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49479/isro2007-09\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Let A be the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix}3 &amp;1 \\\\ 1&amp;2\\end{bmatrix}\\). What is the maximum value of \\(x^TAx\\) where the maximum is taken over all x that are the unit eigenvectors of A? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(5 + \\sqrt{5})}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(5 - \\sqrt{5})}{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(5 + \\sqrt{5})}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3433/gate2007-it-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a 4 x 4 matrix with eigenvalues -5, -2, 1, 4. Which of the following is an\neigenvalue of <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} A &amp; I\\\\ I&amp;A \\end{bmatrix}\\)<br>  where I is the 4 x 4 identity matrix? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-7</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1223/gate2007-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>What are the eigenvalues of the matrix P given below <br>\\(P= \\begin{pmatrix} a &amp;1 &amp;0 \\\\ 1&amp; a&amp; 1\\\\ 0&amp;1 &amp;a \\end{pmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(a, a -\\sqrt2, a + \\sqrt2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a, a, a</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0, a, 2a</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-a, 2a, 2a</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(a, a -\\sqrt2, a + \\sqrt2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3565/gate2006-it-26\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>F is an nxn real matrix. b is an nx1 real vector. Suppose there are two nx1\nvectors, u and v such that u\\(\\neq\\)v , and Fu=b, Fv=b.\nWhich one of the following statements is false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Determinant of F is zero</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>There are an infinite number of solutions to Fx = b</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There is an x\\(\\neq\\)0 such that Fx = 0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>F must have two identical rows</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>F must have two identical rows</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/984/gate2006-23#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the polynomial \\(p(x)=a_{0}+a_{1}x+a_{2}x^{2} + a_{3}x^{3}\\), where \\(a_{i}\\neq 0,\\forall i\\). The minimum number of multiplications needed to evaluate p on an input x is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/792/gate2006-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>The determinant of the matrix given below is<br>\n\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp;1 &amp;0 &amp;2 \\\\ -1&amp; 1&amp; 1&amp; 3\\\\ 0&amp;0 &amp;0 &amp; 1\\\\ 1&amp; -2&amp; 0&amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>-1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3747/gate2005-it-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>What are the eigen values of the following 2 x 2 matrix? <br> \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 2 &amp;-1 \\\\ -4 &amp; 5 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1 and -1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1 and 6</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2 and 5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4 and -1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1 and 6</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1174/gate2005-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following system of equations in three real variables \\(x_1, x_2 \\; and \\; x_3 \\) : <br><br>\n\\(2x_1 - x_2 + 3x_3 = 1\\)<br>\n\\(3x_1 + 2x_2 + 5x_3 = 2\\) <br>\n\\(-x_1 + 4x_2 + x_3 = 3\\)<br><br>\nThe system of equations has <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>no solution</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a unique solution</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>more than one but a finite number of solutions</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>an infinite number of solutions</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>a unique solution</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1173/gate2005-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If matrix \\(X = \\begin{bmatrix} a &amp; 1 \\\\ -a^2+a-1 &amp; 1-a \\end{bmatrix}\\)  and \\(X^2 - X + I = O\\) (\\(I\\) is the identity matrix and \\(O\\) is the zero matrix), then the inverse of \\(X\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1-a &amp;-1 \\\\ a^2&amp; a \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1-a &amp;-1 \\\\ a^2-a+1&amp; a \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} -a &amp;1 \\\\ -a^2+a-1&amp; 1-a \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^2-a+1 &amp;a \\\\ 1&amp; 1-a \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1-a &amp;-1 \\\\ a^2-a+1&amp; a \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3679/gate2004-it-36\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}